Rick Farouni | Curriculum Vitae

ETH Zurich - Department of Biosystems Science and Engineering (D-BSSE)

✓ rfarouni@protonmail.com • ♦ http://rfarouni.github.io/

I am an applied statistician and bioinformatics scientist with expertise in the statistical modeling and bioinformatics analysis of genomics, single-cell transcriptomics (scRNA-seq), and CRISPR genome editing data.

Experience

Bioinformatics Scientist

The Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in Zurich (ETH Zurich)

Research Lab of Dr. Platt, Department of Biosystems Science and Engineering

10/2020-Present

Postdoctoral Researcher

McGill University-Génome Québec Innovation Centre

Quebec, Canada 06/2018-09/2020

Research Lab of Dr. Najafabadi, Department of Human Genetics

Massachusetts General Hospital-Harvard Medical School

Massachusetts, USA 06/2017-05/2018

Research Lab of Dr. Pinello, Molecular Pathology Unit

- The Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard (Affiliated Member)

Research Intern

Department of Biomedical Informatics Summer Internship Program

Research Lab of Dr. Ewy Mathè, The Ohio State University

Ohio, USA 05/2016-08/2016

University Teaching Assistant.....

The Ohio State University

Graduate Teaching Associate (Statistics)

Ohio, USA 2013-2017

Served as a Teaching Assistant for three courses:

- Repeated Measures Models
- Covariance Structure Models
- Data Analysis in Psychology

Education

Academic Qualifications

PhD in Quantitative Psychology (i.e. Applied Statistics)

Ohio, USA

The Ohio State University

2015-2017

Dissertation Topic: 'Application of Deep Latent Generative Models to the Unsupervised Learning of Chromatin States'

Master of Science in Mathematical Statistics

Ohio, USA

The Ohio State University

2012-2015

Master's Degree in Psychometrics

Ohio, USA

The Ohio State University

2012-2014

Thesis Project: 'Latent Variable Modeling of Categorical Item Responses in a Hierarchical Bayesian Framework'

Bachelor's Degree in Psychology

Pennsylvania, USA

The Pennsylvania State University

2011-2012

Publications

Journal Papers (first author/co-author).....

- o **Farouni, R.**, Djambazian, H., Ferri, L. E., Ragoussis, J., and Najafabadi, H. S. (2020). Model-based analysis of sample index hopping reveals its widespread artifacts in multiplexed single-cell RNA-sequencing. *Nature Communications*. Paper available at https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-020-16522-z. Website: https://csglab.github.io/PhantomPurgeR/.
- o Clement, K.†, **Farouni, R.**†, Bauer, D. E., and Pinello, L. (2018). Design and analysis of unique molecular identifiers for deep amplicon sequencing. **Bioinformatics**. https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bty264. Preprint available at https://www.biorxiv.org/content/biorxiv/early/2018/03/23/288118.full.pdf
- o Pinello, L.[†], **Farouni, R.**[†], and Yuan, G-C. (2018). Haystack: systematic analysis of the variation of epigenetic states and cell-type specific regulatory elements. *Bioinformatics*. https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bty031. Preprint available at https://doi.org/10.101/199067
- o Baskin, E.[†], **Farouni, R.**[†], and Mathè, E. (2017). ALTRE: workflow for defining ALTered Regulatory Elements using chromatin accessibility data. *Bioinformatics*. https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btx386. Preprint available at http://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2016/10/14/080564.full.pdf+html

Journal Papers (middle author).....

o Anderson-Trocmé, L., **Farouni, R.**, Bourgey, M., Kamatani, Y., Higasa, K., Seo, J., Kim, C., Matsuda, F., Gravel, S. (2019). Legacy Data Confounds Genomics Studies. *Molecular Biology*

- and Evolution. https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msz201
- Seruggia, D., Oti, M., Tripathi, P., Canver, M. C., LeBlanc, L., Di Giammartino, D. C., Bullen, M.J., Nefzger C.M., Sun, Y.B.Y., Farouni, R., Polo, J.M., Pinello, L., Apostolou, E., Kim J., Orkin, S.H., and Das, P.P. (2019). TAF5L and TAF6L Maintain Self-Renewal of Embryonic Stem Cells via the MYC Regulatory Network. *Molecular Cell*.
- Clement K., Rees H., Canver, M.C., Gehrke J. M., Farouni, R., Hsu, J.Y., Cole, M., Liu D.R., Joung J.K., Bauer, D.E., Pinello, L. (2019). CRISPResso2 provides accurate and rapid genome editing sequence analysis. *Nature Biotechnology*.
- Hsu, J. Y., Fulco, C.P., Cole, M., Canver, M.C., Pellin D., Sher, F, Farouni, R., Clement K., Biasco L., Engreitz, J.M., Lander, E.S., Joung J.K., Bauer, D.E., Pinello, L. (2018). CRISPR-SURF: Exploratory and interactive software for analyzing CRISPR-based tiling screens. *Nature Methods*.

Consortium Journal Papers (contributor).....

o Grüning, B., Dale, R., Sjödin, A., Rowe, J., Chapman, B. A., Tomkins-Tinch, C. H., The Bioconda Team, and Köster, J.(2018). Bioconda: A sustainable and comprehensive software distribution for the life sciences. *Nature Methods*. (Bioconda team member contributor, ranked 94 in the consortium author list).

Preprints....

Farouni, R. (2017). A Contemporary Overview of Probabilistic Latent Variable Models. arXiv preprint. Preprint available at https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.08137

Dissertation and Thesis

- o Farouni, R. (2017). Application of Deep Latent Generative Models to the Unsupervised Learning of Chromatin States. *PhD Dissertation*. Manuscript available at https://etd.ohiolink.edu/!etd.send_file?accession=osu1492189894812539&disposition=inline
- o Farouni, R. (2014). Latent Variable Models of Categorical Responses in the Bayesian and Frequentist Frameworks. *Masters Thesis*. Manuscript available at https://etd.ohiolink.edu/!etd.send_file?accession=osu1412374136&disposition=inline

Conference Presentations

Joint Statistical Meetings

Seattle

Poster Presentation

2015

Poster Title: Across-Subject Predictive Modeling of fMRI BOLD Responses to Faces using a sparse Bayesian Group Factor Analysis Model (available at https://rfarouni.github.io/assets/posters/jsm2015.pdf).

Software Development

o PhantomPurgeR: The optimal purging of phantom molecules by the robust estimation of the sample index hopping rate in multiplexed droplet-based single-cell RNA-seq data. GitHub Repo: https://csglab.github.io/PhantomPurgeR/.

- o Haystack: A Python bioinformatics pipeline for the identification of genomic regions of epigenetic variability across different cell-types, cell-type specific cis-regulatory elements, and their associated transcription factors. GitHub Repo: https://github.com/pinellolab/haystack_bio.
- o ALTRE: A Workflow for Identifying ALTered Regulatory Elements using Chromatin Accessibility Data. GitHub Repo: https://github.com/Mathelab/ALTRE.

Awards and Fellowships

0	Graduate Student Conference Presentation Award The Ohio State University	2015
0	The Center for Cognitive and Brain Sciences Summer Graduate Fellowship The Ohio State University	2015
	Project Proposal : 'Decoding the Pixels of the Face Image from the Voxels of fMRI BOLD Activity Patterns'	
0	The Social and Behavioral Sciences Summer Fellowship The Ohio State University	2014
0	University Fellowship The Ohio State University	2012

Technical Skill Set

- Statistics and Machine Learning
 - **Scientific Programming Languages:** Proficient in and comfortable transitioning between *R* and *Python* depending on computing goals. Familiar with *Julia*.
 - Deep Learning Frameworks: Experienced in using Pytorch, Tensorflow, and Keras.
 - Probabilistic Programming Languages: Proficient in Stan, familiar with Edward.
- o **Bioinformatics Software:** Analysis of next generation sequencing data, R's Bioconductor core packages, Bowtie2, bedtools.
- Cluster and High-Performance Computing: Good knowledge of running bioinformatics analysis pipelines on super-computing clusters.
- Web and Software Development Tools: LaTeX, Linux OS, Git, Docker, and Bash. Basic knowledge in website development tools such as HTML, CSS, and Jekyll.

Journal Review Service

Psychometrika Ad Hoc Reviewer	2015
Psychological Methods Ad Hoc Reviewer	2016